Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Northern/Spanish Morocco, 1720-1957; Series V
  - Tétouan
    - Document regarding ownership of courtyard, 1846; MS.1825.0319; 4 pages (2 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Yaakov Nahon and Yosef ha-Kohen.
    - Letter from someone interested in studying to become a scribe for the court, 1931; MS.1825.0320; 1 leaf; 22 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Place: Tétouan. The letter was written by Avraham Bibas and sent to Mosheh ibn Danan in Fès. The letter includes a request for purchasing a book.
    - Document regarding a real estate transaction, 1904; MS.1825.0325; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Shemuel Laredo and Shemuel Bargilon.
    - Announcement of the rabbinic court of Tétouan with regard to various issues pertaining to the Jewish community, 1840?; MS.1825.0353; 8 pages (1 blank); 21 centimeters (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Place: Tétouan. The document has the signature of Yitshak Nahon and other important rabbis.
    - Document concerning distribution of money to the poor, 1902; MS.1825.0357; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Legal document concerning inheritance and levirate marriage, 1912; MS.1825.0358; 4 pages (2 blank); 28 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Yaakov Bentolila and Khalfon Rofe.
    - Legal document concerning the engagement of Shemuel ben Harosh and Klara Wahnun, 1874; MS.1825.0360; 4 pages (3 blank); 24 centimeters. Damaged, with some loss of text. (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Document concerning ownership of a store, 1865; MS.1825.0361.1; 4 pages (1 blank); 18 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Document concerning ownership of a store, 1869; MS.1825.0361.2; 2 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Testimony concerning a store, 1868; MS.1825.0361.3; 2 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Legal document concerning a debt, 1846; MS.1825.0362; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Legal document, 1891; MS.1825.0363.2; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Place: Tétouan. Gibraltar is mentioned.
    - Legal document, 1915; MS.1825.0364; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Document concerning money and real estate, 1887; MS.1825.0365; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Document concerning a courtyard, 1879; MS.1825.0366; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Legal document assigning power of attorney to Yitshak ben Walid, 1888; MS.1825.0367; 1 leaf; 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Document concerning inheritance, 1880; MS.1825.0368; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. Fragile. Smaller sheet is taped to it. (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Legal document, 1905; MS.1825.0369; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Legal document concerning inheritance, 1900; MS.1825.0370; 4 pages (2 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Legal document, 1899; MS.1825.0371; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Legal document regarding remarriage after the death of a man's first wife, 1873; MS.1825.0372.1; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 15)
      Place: Tétouan. Document MS.1825.0372.2 also refers to the same man.
    - Legal document, 1880; MS.1825.0372.2; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 15)
      Place: Tétouan. The document pertains to the man mentioned in document MS.1825.0372.1.
    - Legal document regarding a financial claim, 1846 or 1847; MS.1825.0373; 4 pages (2 blank); 29 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Legal document concerning inheritance, 1837; MS.1825.0376; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Reuven Almalih and Avraham Anhori.
    - Legal document written by a woman, 1856; MS.1825.0378; 4 pages (1 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Legal document concerning a financial matter, 1832; MS.1825.0379; 4 pages (2 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1827; MS.1825.0382; 4 pages (2 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1830; MS.1825.0383; 4 pages (1 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1835; MS.1825.0384; 4 pages (2 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1839; MS.1825.0385; 4 pages (2 blank); 13 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1843; MS.1825.0386; 4 pages (2 blank); 17 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1845; MS.1825.0387; 4 pages (1 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1888; MS.1825.0388; 4 pages (2 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1883; MS.1825.0389; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1898; MS.1825.0390; 4 pages (2 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1908; MS.1825.0391; 4 pages (3 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1921; MS.1825.0392; 4 pages (3 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1921; MS.1825.0393; 4 pages (1 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1928; MS.1825.0394; 4 pages (3 blank); 36 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Document relating to commercial transactions, 1933; MS.1825.0395; 4 pages (3 blank); 34 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Document concerning a legal dispute, 1822; MS.1825.0409; 2 pages; 29 centimeters. Paper torn with worm holes and some loss of text. (Box 12, Folder 20)
      Place: Tétouan. The judge is Yosef Almaliah. The witnesses are Yehudah Almalih and Avraham Anhori. The case is between [?] Ha-Levi and the widow of Yosef Khalfon.
    - Condolences to Yosef Bibas of Tétouan, 1720; MS.1825.0411; 2 pages; 14 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 21)
      Place: Tétouan. On the other side of the page is a letter signed by Shalem ibn Tsur.
    - Letter with regard to the betrothal of Zaharah, the daughter of Mosheh Ben Hamu, to Yosef Benzaken of Tangier, 1922; MS.1825.0451; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 21)
      Place: Tétouan. The letter is signed by Yaakov Bentolila and Yaakov Ben Illouz. The letter is confirmed by Yitshak Vidal ha-Sarfati from Tétouan.
    - Letter with regard to the appropriate wording of a bill of divorce, 1890; MS.1825.0461.1-.2; 8 pages (4 blank); 26 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 2)
      Place: Tétouan. The letter is sent by Shemuel Nahon of Tétouan to Mordekhai Bengio of Tangier.
    - Document sent to Yehudah Elbaz, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0495; 2 pages; 14 x 20 centimeters. Worm-eaten with loss of text. (Box 12, Folder 21)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by [Yaakov ben Simhon?]
    - Document concerning the paying off of a debt, 1827; MS.1825.0516; 4 pages (1 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 22)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Yaakov Nahon and Avraham Anhori.
    - Letter of condolences to Rabbi Ben Walid on the death of his wife, 1913; MS.1825.0527; 4 pages (3 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Document in Judeo-Spanish, 1836; MS.1825.0544; 4 pages (2 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 22)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Refael Lasri.
    - Document regarding an inheritance, 1879; MS.1825.0554; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 23)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Menahem Parienti and Yaakov ha-Levi.
    - Document relating to an inheritance, 1874, 1911; MS.1825.0556; 4 pages; 23 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 3)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Vidal ben Marag'. The document continues on the second page followed by an additional document from 1911 signed by Shemuel Illouz and Shem Tov Nahon.
    - Document with regard to an inheritance, 1879; MS.1825.0557; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 23)
      Place: Tétouan. Mazal Tov, the widow of Barukh ben Eliyahu Lasri, gave her son Yosef control over a quarter of her property to reach a settlement with her husband's business partner, Maimon ben Shitrit.The document is signed by Menahem Pariente and Yaakov ha-Levi.
    - Letter in Judeo-Spanish written by [Yitshak Pariente?] to Yitshak ben Walid, 1913; MS.1825.0582; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Document signed by Hayim Khalfon and Refael Shemuel Laredo, 1898; MS.1825.0583; 4 pages (2 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 24)
      Place: Tétouan. Gilbraltar is mentioned.
    - Document regarding possesion of a store, 1862, 1863; MS.1825.0595; 4 pages (1 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 3)
      Place: Tétouan. On the verso is a document dated 1863 belonging to Shemuel ben Shitrit concerning the mortgage of a house. The document is signed by Reuven Almalih.
    - Document detailing the allocation of funds of the synagogue She'erit Yosef, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0596; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. Bottom of sheet is torn off. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. Yosef Ashriki is mentioned. The document may come from Tétouan.
    - Copies of two documents concerning ownership of stores, 1879, 1884; MS.1825.0599; 4 pages (2 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. The first document (page 1) was written in Tétouan in 1879 and was signed by Halfon Hadzouel and Shemuel ben Illoz. The second document (page 2) was written in 1884 in Tangier and was certified again in 1925.
    - Document concerning collateral and inheritance, 1894; MS.1825.0689; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Yitshak Bargel and Yitshak Shukrun.
    - Document regarding inheritance, 1881; MS.1825.0690; 4 pages (2 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Place: Tétouan. Yitshak Abukatsif left half of his inheritance to his brother and the other half to his widow after the brother, Yehudah, performed the release from levirate marriage (halitsah)
    - Document regarding a donation to the Talmud Torah, 1857; MS.1825.0691; 1 leaf; 18 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Place: Tétouan. An important document regarding a donation (Hekdesh) made by Yitshak Ben Walid's wife to the Talmud Torah.
    - Document regarding transfer of funds to a widow, 1856 or 1857; MS.1825.0692; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 26)
      Place: Tétouan. A document concerning transfer of money to Masudah, the widow of Makhluf ben Ittah from Ksar-el-Kebir. Yitshak Ben Walid is mentioned in the document.
    - Document affirming a pledge for donation, 1850; MS.1825.0693; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 26)
      Place: Tétouan. The pledge for the donation was made by Ester bat Avraham Salmah.
    - Legal decisions concerning inheritance, 1861, 1863; MS.1825.0716; 4 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. Two legal decisions relating to inheritance. The first decision is by Abraham Anqāwa in 1861 and the second is by Shemaya Rofe and Menahem Pariente in 1863.
    - Letter concerning bill of divorce, 1873; MS.1825.0717; 4 pages; 30 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. A letter written by Yitshak Nahon, an important rabbi of Tétouan, with regard to a bill of divorce.
    - Legal document with regard to an inn, 1916; MS.1825.0785; 4 pages (2 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. A long list of people are mentioned here. Signed by Vidal Yisrael.
    - Legal document, 1833; MS.1825.0823; 1 page; 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 26)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Shelomoh Nahon, Mosheh Tavril, Barukh Lasri, David Ben Harosh and Shemaya Rofe.
    - Legal document with regard to a loan, 1828; MS.1825.0827; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Two legal documents signed by rabbis of Tétouan, 1826; MS.1825.0829; 4 pages (1 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 27)
      Place: Tétouan. Names mentioned in the document are Yosef ben Aadi, Barukh Lasri, Yaakov ben Shitrit, Yaakov [?] and Avraham ha-Levi.
    - Legal document of the brothers David and Maimon ben Elisha, 1839; MS.1825.0831; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Legal document, 1831; MS.1825.0834; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Avraham Amram, Barukh Lasri, and Shemuel Pimiento and Shelomoh Coriat.
    - Legal document, 1834; MS.1825.0835; 4 pages (3 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Yitshak ben Shukrun, Barukh Lasri, Mosheh Coriat and Avraham Anhori.
    - Legal document, 1835; MS.1825.0836; 4 pages (3 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Avraham Sito, Avraham Anhori and and Haym Ben Shitrit.
    - Document with regard to sons who do not respect their father, 1845; MS.1825.0855; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 29)
      Place: Tétouan. The owner of the document is Abraham Abulafia.
    - Legal document, 1838-1897; MS.1825.0874; 2 pages; 38 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Yosef Aburabia and Mosheh ben Asulin.
    - Letter including details of a sale, 1879; MS.1825.1043; 4 pages (2 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 29)
      Place: Tétouan. The letter was written to the judge Mordekhai Bengio by Yitshak Nahon.
    - Document concerning cancellation of a gift deed, 1871; MS.1825.1046; 4 pages (3 blank); 29 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Document with regard to the dowry and the betrothal of Simhah Yisrael to a man from the Abecassis family, 1883; MS.1825.1048; 4 pages (3 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 30)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is written in Hebrew and signed by Menahem Parienti and Mosheh Ben Asulin.
    - Legal decision with regard to issues of inheritance, 1826; MS.1825.1194; 4 pages (2 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by witnesses and rabbis of Tétouan.
    - Seven documents of the rabbinic court that deal with the estate of the deceased Mosheh Taurel from the city of Tétouan, 1824-1833; MS.1825.1195; 7 documents, each 4 pages (some blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 31)
      Place: Tétouan. The matter raised an interesting discussion which is included in these papers. The documents were signed by Mosheh Coriat, Avraham Anhori and others.
    - Letter of guarantee signed by witnesses and rabbis of Tétouan, 1836; MS.1825.1196; 4 pages (2 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Place: Tétouan. Avraham Anhori is one of the signatories.
    - Letter from a rabbinic court with regard to the estate of the widow G'imal Abudraham, 1843; MS.1825.1197; 4 pages (3 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Shemaya Rofe and Eliyahu Abudraham.
    - Letter with regard to a gift from the estate of Barukh Lasri, 1890; MS.1825.1198; 4 pages (2 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Refael Shemuel Laredo and [?] Khalfon.
    - Legal decision with regard to a piece of property given through inheritance to Eliyahu Lasri, 1857; MS.1825.1199; 4 pages (1 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Place: Tétouan. Legal intervention was required because the piece of property that was given to Eliyahu Lasri was close to another piece of property. Avraham Anhori is one of the signatories.
    - Legal decision concerning inheritance, 1857; MS.1825.1201; 4 pages (1 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Place: Tétouan. The scribe who wrote the document mentioned the name Shelomoh ibn Walid. Avraham Anhori is one of the signatories.
    - Collateral given by Khalfon Haguel, 1868; MS.1825.1204; 4 pages (2 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Legal issues relating to inheritance between Khalfon Haguel and his father-in-law Menahem Pariente, 1887; MS.1825.1205; 4 pages (2 blank); 24 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 33)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by Refael Shemuel Laredo and others.
    - Issues relating to collateral in the court, 1891; MS.1825.1206; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 33)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by witnesses and rabbis.
    - Introduction to a homily with regard to text from the Book of Job "Sava'nu Nedudim", 1890?; MS.1825.1207; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Letter concerning the betrothal of Ezra ben Shelomoh ha-Kohen, 1872; MS.1825.1208; 4 pages (3 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 34)
      Place: Tétouan. The letter details an obligation for payment of the fee.
    - Legal decision with regard to a guarantee of Makhluf Shukrun, 1879; MS.1825.1210; 4 pages (1 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Legal decision with regard to a known person doing business, 1883, 1886; MS.1825.1211; 4 pages (1 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 34)
      Place: Tétouan. The document was reaffirmed three years after it was originally written. It is signed by Mosheh Gabizon and Mosheh Azuelos.
    - Document with regard to the estate of Shelomoh ha-Kohen, 1878; MS.1825.1212; 2 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 34)
      Place: Tétouan. Signed by two rabbis from Tétouan.
    - Document of a rabbinic court in Tétouan attesting to an acquisition, 1880; MS.1825.1214; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. Damaged with some loss of text. (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Betrothal document of Avraham Tseruya to Zahara Oliel, 1887; MS.1825.1215; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Legal document, 1892?; MS.1825.1217; 4 pages (2 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - Receipt from the Talmudic academy "Meah Shearim" in Jerusalem, 1911; MS.1825.1219; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 36)
      Place: Tétouan. The receipt was sent to Yitshak Bargilon in Tétouan. The stamp of the Talmudic academy is on the document.
    - Rental agreement concerning a courtyard, 1838; MS.1825.1508; 4 pages (2 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 37)
      Place: Tétouan. The two witnesses were Avraham Gabizon and Yahya ben Oliel.
    - Document concerning a debt, 1863; MS.1825.1511; 4 pages (2 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 37)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Menahem Pariente and Khalfon Haguel. The document has special importance because Haguel was the uncle of Solika the righteous. According to tradition Solika refused to marry a Muslim ruler and convert to Islam and as a result was stoned to death.
    - Document concerning the sale of a courtyard, 1911; MS.1825.1518; 4 pages (1 blank); 16 centimeters. (Box 12, Folder 37)
      Place: Tétouan. The document is signed by Reuven Almalih and Yitshak Bibas.
  - Tangier
    - Document concerning the cancellation of an engagement, 1886; MS.1825.0046; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Place: Tangier. Agreement between Shimon Abudarham from Tangier and the young man Shimon ha-Kohen from Ouazzane. The document releases Simha, the daughter of Shimon Abudarham, from the engagement and declares that she is now free to marry any Jewish man. Dated 4 Iyar 5646 (9 May 1886).
    - Letter concerning inheritance, 1866; MS.1825.0086; 4 pages (2 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Place: Tangier. A letter written to the great rabbi Abner Israel Sarfati by Mosheh Yitshak Nahon.
    - Letter seeking a rabbinic decision with regard to a business partnership, 1881; MS.1825.0197; 4 pages (1 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Place: Tangier. The case involved appointing a guardian to manage the inheritance of orphans.The document was written in Tangier and sent to Abner Israel ha-Sarfati in Fès. It is signed by David Nehamah.
    - Document concerning money given by a man to his brother for business, 1905; MS.1825.0245; 4 pages (2 blank); 23 centimeters. A hole in the center of the document with some loss of text. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Place: Tangier.
    - Document concerning investments for business, 1885; MS.1825.0296; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Place: Tangier. The document is signed by Yosef Toledano and Avraham Bengio.
    - Document of testimony concerning the death of a man, 1944; MS.1825.0315; 1 leaf; 22 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Place: Tangier. The testimony was given by Yosef Lugasi and Hayim Monsonego with regard to the death of a Jewish man in 1937.
    - Two documents concerning financial matters of married couples, 1938, 1957; MS.1825.0317; 2 pages; 25 centimeters. Tape. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Place: Tangier. One document (pages 1-3) is from 1938, and the second document (page 4) is from 1957.
    - Document regarding property belonging to two partners, 1925; MS.1825.0318; 4 pages (3 blank); 27 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Place: Tangier. The property included land, cattle, sheep and goats, legumes and more. The document is signed by Yehudah Azencot and Akivah Akiva Sananes. The document is stamped with the seal of of Yehudah ben Shimol.
    - Document regarding a court decision on a change in the terms of a marriage agreement, 1938; MS.1825.0321; 4 pages (1 blank); 25 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Place: Tangier. The document is signed by Makhluf Elkobi and Yemin ha-Kohen. The document is certified by Yehudah Azencot.
    - Letter of condolence, 1913; MS.1825.0326; 4 pages (3 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Place: Tangier. The letter was sent by Yehudah Azencot to Yitshak ben Walid in Tétouan consoling him on the death of his wife.
    - Letter in Judeo-Arabic written in Tangier to Avraham Ben Shoshan in Fès regarding a request for a lawyer, 1919; MS.1825.0334; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Place: Tangier. The request was for a lawyer to represent a woman. The woman's name is Gracia. Shaul Ben Shoshan signed and added his request for a lawyer because he could not find one in Rabat or Casablanca.
    - Legal document, 1885; MS.1825.0356; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Legal document concerning the implementation of legal decisions and contracts, 1900; MS.1825.0359; 4 pages (2 blank); 31 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Letter concerning a childless widow awaiting levirate marriage (yevamah) and a certificate of divorce, 1863; MS.1825.0374; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Place: Tangier. The letter was sent from Tangier to Yitshak Ben Walid (Isaac Bengualid) in Tétouan.
    - Copy of a legal document, 1868; MS.1825.0380; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Place: Tangier. There are several dates, the latest of which is 1868.
    - Collection of documents, 1847, 1857, 1861; MS.1825.0381; 4 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Legal discussion by the chief rabbi of Tangier concerning the admissibility in court of circumstantial evidence, 1912; MS.1825.0440; 4 pages (1 blank); 32 centimeters. (Box 34, Folder 2)
      Place: Tangier. Signed by Mordekhai Bengio, chief rabbi of Tangier. Some of the greatest thinkers in halakhah are mentioned, such as Asher ben Jehiel (Rosh), Maimonides, etc., as well as Moroccan Rabbis such as Jacob ben Reuben ibn Ẓur (Ya'bets).
    - Court record containg two legal decisions, 1922; MS.1825.0442; 1 leaf; 28 centimeters. (Box 13, Folder 6)